Professor Dave here, let's talk about the
third law of thermodynamics.
We've gone through three of the laws of
thermodynamics, which leaves just one to
go, and the third law of thermodynamics
deals with another strange concept: the
idea of a temperature of absolute zero.
We know that temperatures can get very
hot and very cold, but not everyone is
familiar with the idea of the coldest
possible temperature. However, with our
new understanding of heat and
temperature, it should make perfect sense.
We know that temperature is a measure of
available heat energy, which is just a
collection of kinetic energies of motion.
We know that as the temperature
decreases, the internal energy of a
system decreases, as does the kinetic
energy of each particle. As the
temperature becomes very cold, particles
slow to a complete stop, and there is no
more kinetic energy. No more kinetic
energy of motion means no more
temperature by any real definition of
the term, so we will call this absolute
zero. At absolute zero, every substance
would be a solid, even things like
hydrogen and helium, and one way of
summarizing the third law of
thermodynamics is by saying that the
entropy of any crystalline substance at
absolute zero will be equal to zero. This
is a necessary consequence of
Boltzmann's equation, S equals k times
the natural log of W. If there is no
kinetic energy, nothing is moving, so
there is only one possible microstate
that the particles can inhabit. With a
value for W equal to one, the natural log
of 1 is 0, so at absolute zero the
entropy of any substance must also be
zero. However, absolute zero can never
truly be reached, which is communicated
in a rephrasing of the third law which
states that it is impossible to lower
the temperature of any system to
absolute zero in a finite number of steps.
Satisfactory analysis of this law will
require the quantum mechanical
zero-point energy, and will thus have to
wait until the modern physics course.
This concludes our analysis of the laws
of thermodynamics, a near mythical
accomplishment in the history of science.
It also means we have covered some of
the harder stuff in physics, so now we
get to move on to fun things like waves
and magnets. But first, let's check comprehension.
Thanks for watching, guys. Subscribe to my channel for
more tutorials, support me on patreon so I can
keep making content, and as always feel
free to email me: